Well, if Moore's law puts a lot more
transistors in a chip, how come they're
not getting hotter and hotter?
>> This is David Patterson, Turing [music]
award winner, famous for his
contributions to computer architecture.
And we discussed the historic risk
versus CISK debate
>> and he said and CISK won. Well, that's a
pretty myopic view. Everything is energy
bound now. Register [snorts] allocation
by the [music] compilers was so poor
>> and his thoughts on modern GPU and TPU
architecture. What's the highle
differences between a CPU, [music]
a GPU, and a TPU?
>> What they realize for machine learning
and AI?
>> Here's the full episode.
Maybe you could explain risk versus CISK
kind of like what that debate was and
why was it controversial.
What happened is in kind of in you know
the microprocessor was invented in the
1970s and but in the beginning it was
basically a toy. It'd be something that
would go in microwaves and things like
that. Those of us who believed in
Moore's law believed eventually the uh
microprocessor would be the way we did
all our computing with the doubling of
transistors every year or two.
eventually there'd be enough transistors
that on one of these microprocessors
would be a serious computer.
So the people who were designing
microprocessors like in Intel and Texas
Instruments weren't really computer
architects. So they just imitated what
the big companies did. So companies
leading companies like IBM or at the
time digital equipment corporation uh
IBM for mainframes digital equipment for
what were called minicomp computers they
kind of drove the uh architecture the
instruction set design. So what they
were doing with Morris law was building
more and more sophisticated
u instructions. They had they had you
know mini computers be the size of a a
refrigerator or a couple of
refrigerators and mainframes would be
the size of many of those. So that's
what they were doing with more hard
sources. And the philosophy at the time
was that by having a more sophisticated
instruction set you kind of raise the
level of abstraction closer to the
software. So that had some inherent
benefits over having something at a
lower level. Now from a c some of us uh
who were in that area like my friend
John Hennessy at Stanford and I we
thought that wasn't necessarily the
right thing to do. Compilers would go
from programming languages down to the
instruction set. So why couldn't
compilers hold that? And then the
question is what's the right instruction
set for this emerging microprocessor?
And the prevailing wisdom of these more
sophisticated instruction sets, complex
instruction sets. And if you think of it
like a vocabulary, it was like a having
lots of polyelabic words in your
vocabulary, you know. And the
alternative was going to be what we
called the reduced instruction set
computer was having lots of reduced
instructions like monoselabic words. So
you might guess that for a program to
execute these instructions, if they're
simpler, they take more of them and if
they're sophisticated, they take fewer,
but the sophisticated ones might take
longer to run. So kind of the question
came down to what was that ratio? Um,
and in the in the beginning in the 1980s
when these debates were happening, there
was this kind of very viciferous debates
partly of like what those ratios are
going to do, but a big part was kind of
philosophical. Weren't weren't you doing
damage to the software industry by
lowering the instruction set level? So
the gap between the programming
languages and the instruction set was
larger. That was kind of the ferocity of
the debates. Well, after the dust
settled a few years later and we started
getting numbers, it turned out you
needed like maybe 30% 40% more simple
instructions to execute in a program,
but you could run them four or five
times faster. So the net was, you know,
or five times faster say. So 3 or 4x
speed up was the potential for risk over
CISK.
>> You mentioned that um I guess
philosophical difference like that gap.
Why why would that be controversial?
>> I mean unfortunately I'd say computer
architecture in the 1970s and even 1980s
a lot of it was uh was kind of people
designed this by using their intuition
or using their gut. Their feelings was
this is the right thing to do. And even
the textbooks of the time were like
cataloges. They here's a computer and
just list all its features and here's
another computer listing all its
features. So it's pretty dissatisfying
what was going on because these debates
it would seem like we ought to be able
to sign this, you know, scientifically
with with numbers that are there. But
absence of that, it was more like a
philosophical debate like how many
angels on the head of a pin, right? You
could you could have arguments
qualitatively but you couldn't settle
the arguments and because there wasn't
ways to settle the arguments
quantitatively you know people would
just argue about it. Would you say that
you know risk versus cisk did one side
win the war? Yeah. I was just reading
there's some guy online who uh revisited
it and he said and CISK won. Well,
that's a pretty myopic view is uh in the
PC era because of the importance of u
distributing software in binary. So once
the x86 was established and people the
PCs would would ship software in
binaries that was very hard to overcome.
That was a huge uh impediment to
changing the instruction set. So PCs are
design defined by the x86 architecture
largely.
But about also in the 1980s there's this
company in England u that wanted to do a
personal computer they call it was the
acorn personal computer and they decided
they wanted to have their own they
needed their own instruction set
architecture to do that their own chip
they were unsatis the chips they had
available at the time they were doing it
weren't fast enough and they were
influenced by the papers that we did at
Berkeley and so they built what they
called the acorn risk machine
and then uh one of the benefits of this
kind of reduced instruction set is that
it could be simpler, it would take less
resources and take less energy to
execute. And then several years later
when Apple was looking for a
microprocessor that could power, you
know, one of their personal devices that
this one was called the early forerunner
of the iPhone called the Newton. They
came to this company and said, "Boy, I
really like it. Uh, let's get rid of the
Acorn name." So they renamed it the
acorn wrist machine arm and they
recristened it the advanced wrist
machine uh because to get rid of the
acorn and then Apple used it um in the
Newton. Now the new wasn't a commercial
success but it demonstrated the benefits
for risk architecture for mobile
devices. So the Nokia came along just a
few years later with their GDM uh
cellular phone which is one of the first
popular ones and they embraced ARM. And
so ever since you know uh ARM has
dominated all the mobile devices. So I
think I just checked there's been 350
billion
uh ARM processors microprocessors with
ARM technology in it today. So it's like
today 99% of all processors in computers
are risk
even in personal computers. Apple
switched over to ARM from from the x86
architecture. So even PCs there's um
there's a risk architecture is you know
is significant and it's trying to
starting to get in the cloud. The
cloud's largely been defined by the x86
server architectures but um Amazon and I
think Amazon, Microsoft and Google all
have their own development of ARM
processors. So ARM is becoming or risk
processor becoming more popular in the
cloud. So right now you I'd say the x86
architecture market is shrinking while
the risk architecture market is um you
know growing leaps and bounds.
>> Well, how how could someone say CISK one
when you mentioned like 99%
>> Yeah. Well, that's just if you if if
they're doing something in history and
they define computers as personal
computers and maybe servers and they go
up through around 2000. If the story
ended then you could well it looks like
a CISK one but you know uh once we get
into this uh postPC era I don't
understand how somebody would reach that
conclusion. [laughter]
>> You mentioned the the energy expenditure
so like um you know risk makes sense in
places or maybe on mobile devices things
like that.
>> Well even in the cloud I mean everybody
cares about we're we're everything is
energy bound now. So it if u you know
these days of course you're not dealing
with millions of transistors but
billions of transistors. So it matters
somewhat less today. There's so many
things going going on that you can hide
that. I mean even what the x86
architecture did is to compete is that
it translated the x86 instructions in
hardware into risk instructions. And so
you had to pay that extra overhead of
that translation step to get risk
instructions and then you could ex any
good ideas that the risk people had that
the x86 could do. But it was worth it
financially for that extra overhead
because of the value of the PC software
base. So it made a lot of sense for
Intel to do that and they did that in
the early 2000s. It you know it was a
it's a great uh commercial idea. Is
there any niche use case where CISK
makes sense? Is there any, you know, is
this an engineering trade-off or CISK is
objectively worse?
>> Yeah. So, if you want to, if we want to
go kind of one level deeper into all of
this, um,
the what was actually going on in, you
know, in designing computers, the hard
part is the control. And so, what
happened is in the beginning, it was
kind of control was kind of ad hoc. you
would figure out uh you put the gates
together to make it to work. Uh a uh one
of the computing pioneers, Maurice
Welks, figured out a more elegant way to
design control. And he said, "Well, we
could just list all the control signals
as the output of a memory and we could
have something would keep track of where
we were in the memory and and to issue
those control signals." And he called
this he called the this effort the
instruction the the control signals you
could think of instructions. So he
called that a micro instruction and he
called the programming of those
instructions microprogramming.
So where technology was in the 1960s
that made a fair amount of sense and so
IBM built these so-called micro program
computers. So it was basically an
interpreter with very simple
instructions that would interpret this
much more sophisticated instruction set
above it. But you would play this
interpretation overhead. And classically
you know in computer science
interpreting versus compiling uh is
something like a factor of five or 10.
But given you know the latencies of the
memory technologies and the possibility
of doing this out of readonly memory it
made sense u up until the 60s and 70s
and then but then the kind of the
question came up as came around 1980 is
like is this still a good idea? Should
we have this microode interpreter inside
there? And so the alternative is to
think of well rather than uh we've got
this microode interpreter in there why
don't we just compile directly into
those instructions and that's pretty
close to the to the risk ideas. Uh the
micro instructions themselves used to be
you know like a 100 bits wide and really
complicated. So if you if you make them
not quite so long you make them kind of
more natural still we can we could skip
the interpretation step. So with the you
know going going this level deeper kind
of the question would be today would
people invent an instruction set that
was so sophisticated and needed a
microode interpreter and probably they
wouldn't do that. I mean you could do it
you nothing prevents you from doing it
but you wouldn't want to design an
instruction set that was forced to use a
micro card interpreter. you it might
make sense in some very tiny
applications possibly where you have you
know thousand tens of thousands of
transistors maybe this would a microcode
interpret work but I think nobody today
I don't think anybody's invented an
instruction set in the last 20 years
that u has anything that would need a
microcoded interpreter
>> you mentioned the compiler multiple
times here and it seems like that's a
critical piece that kind of makes risk
work so well can you explain the role of
the compiler and how it manages the
relationship between software and
hardware.
>> Well, you you're writing in a
programming language like C or C++ or
maybe Python and um but the quality of
the code that gets generated is is up to
the compiler if you and a specific
example is that it's useful when you
construct computers to have registers
and those registers are actually kind of
visible in in the assembly language or
the machine language programming.
It can be 8, 16 or 32 these registers
for the people programming that little
level to use. Well, it used to be very
difficult for compilers to to um
allocate registers efficiently when they
computers just weren't fast enough. We
didn't have the algorithms that we could
look at a section of code or a sub
routine or something and say how can we
most efficiently do registers? In fact,
the C programming language which was
invented to do systems programming
in C before that to write an operating
system people wrote them an assembly
language believe it or not and but the
Unix people showed uh Ken Thompson
Dennis Richie showed that we could if we
had a low-level language pretty
low-level language we get the benefits
of writing in something that it's much
easier for humans to understand and
debug
because register allocation by the
compilers was was so poor, they had to
put in the ability for the programmer to
give hints of what variables should go
in registers. It was just easier for
them to have the programmer step in and
say, if the machine had eight registers,
I want these six variables to be in
these registers. Don't leave them in
memory because it runs so much slower.
Registers are so much faster. So, a big
part of u the the CISK the risk argument
was the compiler algorithms are getting
better. they could handle these
low-level instructions, they could
allocate registers efficiently.
Uh, and that was, you know, another
reason in these debates about why it
made sense to have a simpler
architecture. What we did in the risk
architectures, well, if registers are
really important, uh, register
allocation really important. One way to
make it easier for the compiler was just
to have a lot more of them. So,
typically the CISK architectures of
times would have eight or maybe 16
registers. So, we we put in 32 and That
was one of the arguments, right, is
well, if it's hard to efficiently use a
small number, let's give them plenty.
So, even if it wasn't that good,
there'll be enough registers. So, most
of the time and and registers weren't
that much more expensive to include in
machines because of MOR's law. I saw
somewhere in in uh one of the talks that
he had given that somehow the compiler
it's it's more easy for it to optimize
the code for risk but in CISK there were
these complex bigger ones and it almost
never used them. Is that a shortcoming
of the compiler? So what happened if we
go back in the compiler days there's
this argument is that by having more
sophisticated instructions this would
raise the level of extraction. that'll
be a smaller gap. They'll make it easy
for the compiler. But that was a
philosophical argument. It it wasn't
something that necessarily compiler
people um could work. Compiler people
weren't making that argument. It was the
architects were making that argument.
And as it turned out when we looked at
the programs when we were doing the
early research on CISK in versus risk is
the compilers didn't really use those
instructions. Often the compiler
writers, the architects would come up
with a sophisticated instruction and the
compiler writers would say, "Well, we
don't need that." In fact, we found
examples where like for a procedure
entry, there'd be a special instruction
built in to do all this work that what
the architects thought the compilers
wanted and the compiler designers say,
"Well, we don't need that. It's it's
faster. It's actually faster for to use
it with separate instructions than use
your sophisticated instruction." And so,
we found a bunch of examples like that.
So you pay the extra overhead of the
microode interpreter to have these
sophisticated instructions and then the
compiler doesn't even use them. Right?
So th this is kind of a nonsensical
situation that that we're in. uh and you
know this is kind of like you know why
why are there startups or why are there
scientific you know breaking points like
that as we looked at all the
technologies with Moore's law you know
ideas like caches with where compilers
were in using sophisticated instructions
the ability to allocate register more
efficiently it made sense to change the
directions away from these microcoded
instruction set architectures to these
simpler architectures
>> when we talk about instruction sets I
mean we're kind assuming that we're
talking about these general purpose
computer are these CPUs and I know GPUs
are kind of talked about a lot and maybe
there's other forms of computing are
there instruction sets for those types
of machines as well.
>> So what happened is around 2000 is when
GPUs came along and these were what we
called domain specific architectures. So
a GPU is a graphics processing unit. It
had one job. it it didn't need to do
everything that a general purpose
processor needs to. Didn't have to
support virtual memory. Uh it didn't
have to support a compiler which is you
know a pretty radical idea for
architectures. It was just for graphics.
And so around 2000 is when Nvidia and
the other GPUs out there because they
were trying to do you know the give you
the graphics for games and give you the
graphics for movies. So it was a niche
product.
So what happened kind of in the computer
industry is it was driven by Moore's law
which I've mentioned many times and also
this lesserk known law called dinard
scaling which is because kind of an
interesting question well if Moore's law
puts a lot more transistors on a chip
how come they're not getting hotter and
hotter as we double the number of
transistors every year and the reason
was this observation made by Bob Dinard
that what as you added more transistors
People would also lower the threshold
voltage which the distinction between a
zero and one and that had like a squared
effect. So you would end up doubling
them transistors but you'd lower the
threshold voltage. So microprocessors
stayed at like 20 or 30 watts. In fact
uh we did a John and I eventually did a
textbook and I was just checking and
that came out in 1990 and we didn't even
talk about power as an issue for the
first three editions. You know, the the
third one came out in 2000. Power wasn't
even a topic because micro dinard
scaling was going on and so
microprocessors stayed in the tens of
watts even as they got faster and
faster. What happened is about 2005 or
so, Dinard scaling stopped working and
that was a shock, right? So, and Intel
actually had a microprocessor that
failed one of their generations because
they just couldn't get the power down
enough. it was too hot to be able to do
that. Um and then so then what that
forced us to go to multicore is that uh
before that it was easiest for the
programmer for everybody if there was
one very sophisticated processor that
did everything but we couldn't do that
anymore. So it went from one
sophisticated processor to two and then
four and then eight simpler processors.
Then it was up to the programmer to
deliver on the potential of Morris law
by paralyzing their code. So we stayed
that way for about another 10 years and
then Moore's law started slowing down.
Uh so that the general purpose
microprocessor was barely improving. It
got a little better but it wasn't
getting dramatically better. Um, in the,
you know, in the 1980s, 1990s, 2000s,
you you have a laptop and your friend's
laptop would be like four times as fast
as yours. And, you know, you were
jealous. So, you would throw away
perfectly good hardware because your
friend's thing was so much faster
because of the rapid change in
performance. Well, that all ended in the
2010s where the you never you wouldn't
throw away a laptop because the new ones
were hardly that much faster than the
old ones. You throw them away when they
break and slow down. Nevertheless,
programmers were used to this dramatic
improvement in performance every few
years because they could add more
features to their software and stuff
like that. So, what were architects
going to do? They'd already done the the
multicore trick in 2005 or so. So around
2015 the idea was we would do domain
specific architectures like the GPUs. So
we if we if you tell me I only have to
run a narrow class of programs and I
don't have to necessarily run all the
operating systems everything else. Well
yes I could shuffle those resources and
do something much more efficient for
something well. So you could do some
things well and there's other things
either you do poorly or not even at all.
So then the question is okay what
domain? So just coincidentally where we
were technologically right around 2012
2015 is when machine learning AI burst
on the scene. Um and so that was it was
evident what domain should we do and the
domain was machine learning AI. So just
coincidentally where we were
technologically
uh this new domain came along and then I
I would say you know I I work for Google
but I think it's fair to say Google was
the one who really uh saw it was the
certainly the first big company who
understood the potential of machine
learning AI and um and bet that they or
feared that they were going to be
swamped with demand and needed to do
custom hardware. So the the translate
tensor processing unit GPU that Google
debuted in 2016 really kind of shocked
the world and got people to realize that
we should be uh designing hardware for
machine learning and we could continue
to improve performance dramatically for
that one domain.
>> What's the high level differences
between a CPU, a GPU and a TPU? the the
CPU has got to be this general purpose
thing. And basically um even today they
have these general purpose cores that
each core is very similar to what the
instruction sets or used to be like 20
years before that. It's not a surprising
design and it's just got lots of cores
and modern ones today could have a h you
know 50 or 100 cores in there. So that's
that's the feature for graphics. uh what
they decided to do which to do the
graphics job is they need to get a lot
of performance on the memory system. So
they went to multi-threading. So they
have hardware threads that you would
send a memory request out and you the
hardware would switch over to do
something else while the when memory is
coming out. So it's this highly threaded
architecture and that's what they
developed and could could run well for
graphics.
um a and graphics. It turns out um
doesn't need very s doesn't need
powerful floating point. It needs
doesn't need wide floating point. So
32-bit floating point is plenty for
graphics even 16 bit. So they were doing
pushing graphics with 16 and 32-bit
floating point in this multi-threaded
kind of architecture. And because it was
kind of its own unique thing, it has its
own own set of terminology
um all to itself. it wasn't kind of out
of the main branch of computer
architecture. Uh so when you look at our
textbooks, we have kind of like a
Rosetta Stone which says here's the
terms that Nvidia uses to describe DP2s.
This is what it means in kind of normal
um well normal in the mainstream
processor design. So they were this
niche product that happened to do pretty
fast um single precision floating point
and uh even half precision floating
point and they were pretty cheap. They
were like hundreds of dollars.
Um
so when people uh so kind of uh but some
people were thinking boy for some
applications if I could turn my program
into like uh pretend that it was doing
creating an image if I could turn my
problem into image generation I could
use these pretty cheap GPUs which had
very good floatingoint performance per
dollar compared to anything else. And so
people started playing around with that.
Uh and uh the founder CEO Jensen Wang
really liked that idea. So in 2006,
he funded an effort to create a
programming language that that would
kind of handle this multi-threaded
hardware architecture that's for
graphics to make it easier to program.
And so that led to the invention of uh
CUDA uh which I can't remember its
acronym but it's really a a proprietary
programming language for the
multi-threaded GPU architecture to make
it kind of easier to program. It was a
it was a C like language but you can't
just compile C programs and run it but
it was C like but people actually liked
it. You know it was certainly much
better than trying to turn your program
into an image generation but people
liked it. But uh Jensen Wang his vision
was try to get these teenagers in the
basement who are playing the games to
learn how to program these things. And
he had a couple of markets that he was
interested in like um you know uh some
of the department of energy labs like uh
fluid flow and some of things like you
know some and he would build special
purpose libraries that could handle that
domain and then use his GPUs to do that
kind of uh special purpose computing but
breaking out of graphics. But that's
kind of the heritage there. Now for the
TPU program um and and so what's
happened uh people started right from
the very beginning people started using
GPUs because they had much better single
precision floatingoint performance than
um than the CPUs. They had a lot more
processors on them. So we had the
potentially much more performance. So
they're kind of one of the breakthrough
moments moments in it was in 2012 when
uh within the machine learning community
this neural networking piece which had a
few advocates but a lot of people didn't
believe in it they went into a
competition to see who could do the best
image recognition in 2012 the so-called
AlexNet beat all the competition this
was this uh historic moment in the in
the in machine learning learning in
neural networking and once they did it
and the guy who did that had taken a
cuda course at the University of Toronto
to learned how to use it and so he says
well as long as I'm doing this I'll do
it on a GPU so he was able to explore a
lot more space on this cheap fast GPU so
he entered it in the competition 2012
and within he was the only one using
neural networks and he crushed the
competition and within a few years
everybody switched over and not only
they were doing neural networks but
they're using GPUs
So GPUs have this um heritage of being a
graphics in graphics engine but more
programmable and uh it started getting
used for machine learning. When Google
came along uh they decided you know it
was a clean slate. They didn't they
didn't care about graphics. So the at
the heart of neural networking is a
matrix multiply. That's the that's the
thing. So they designed a a processor
for at the time microp processor at the
time had a giant matrix multiplying
unit. That was the main thing and then
they threw a bunch of stuff out that
they didn't need. So a lot of general
purpose computing is what's on the chip
is maybe three levels of caches to try
and have so you don't spend all your
time going to the relatively slow
memory. Well, for machine learning, they
knew when their memory accesses were so
they could schedule that. So they didn't
a a hardware cache didn't make any
sense. they would just have a memory
that the software understood would
transfer in time. So those were some of
the innovations. Also they innovated on
the floatingoint format. You didn't need
uh uh you know scientific computing
cares a lot about precision. They have
you know most of it's done in 64-bit
floating point where the exponent is you
know less than 10 bits and most of it is
is the uh precision you know the
fraction can be 50 some bits. Well, they
what they realized for machine learning
and AI, they don't need all that
precision. They needed the range. So,
Google did the first floatingoint format
where the exponent was bigger than the
fraction. That's that was a radical idea
that so-called brain float 16, the part
of Google that was doing this was the
brain research group. So, they brought
out this architecture. They had this
narrow floating point format. They had
big matrix multiply unit. It only had
one one processor in it. uh unlike the
other ones, it was just dedicated
machine learning and it just kind of
blew the doors off of everybody in the
field. It was uh you know like 30 times
better at inference than the
contemporary GPU and 80 times better
than CPU by having this dedicated one.
So when uh Google made this announcement
at their annual retreat a year or so
after um after they had deployed it
inside uh it just shook everybody up.
Intel started buying companies. Um you
know Nvidia started modifying the design
uh for to be mach
learning and then a bunch of other
competitors uh started uh uh
hyperscalers started doing their own
effort. So I think that was the watersh
I think the TPU announcement was the
watershed moment there.
>> So it's it's almost like uh levels of
specialization like the CPU is the most
general. Well yeah if we could still if
you know if we still had dinard scaling
if we you know Morris law and dinard
scaling where we be today with general
purpose processors we should have 100
terahertz
you know microprocessors if we could
build 100 terahertz microprocessors
that's what we do we would the GPUs
would still be a niche you know if we
could do that it you know it raises all
boats that would be fantastic if we
could do that but that that's long in
the history we haven't been able to do
that for 20 years and so you know there
were probably two or three gigahertz
microprocessors in 2005 and that's kind
of where they are barely improved today
so we can't do that. So there's still
areas where it's important to have CPUs.
They're the right, you know, you need
operating systems, compilers and things.
Uh that they're the right solution, but
things have been specialized. And then
now in terms of industry terms, huge
emphasis is being put into the AI
accelerators or just AI in general is
where the money is being invested. And
so the question for any processor
designers was how does my processor
design fit into this AI universe and um
what should I do? How should I change it
for this important application?
>> So you mentioned that kind of Moore's
laws slowing down and I watched this
other talk from Jim Keller saying that
Moore's law isn't isn't dead. But is it
controversial to say that it's slow? Oh,
I mean not not to real engineers. The
the Morris law is very simple. It says
in a in a chip the number of transistors
will double originally said every year
and then he mended it uh to every two
years. Just just look do the chips are
the number of transistors doubled and no
now I think what people assume that
means if trans if we are no longer on
Morris law that technology is not
improving. That's not the same thing.
it's not improving at the rate that
Moore projected. And what was amazing
about Moors law which lasted 50 years is
that it it guided the investment of
semigtory manufacturing. We need to
deliver on doubling transistors every
year or two. How are we going to do
that? How are we going to build the
equipment to do it? So it was a
guideline for the whole industry which
was kind of remarkable. So what we are
doing now is there's pieces of the
technology to get better and there's
pieces that uh that don't improve at
all. So one of the big pieces important
pieces on a chip is the static RAM
SRAMM. So that's hardly improving at
all.
Logic gates still continue to improve.
They are the gates are getting better.
So if you're doing like uh adders or
multipliers, those are getting better.
those pieces. It's not uniform
improvement anymore. And we're also
going to more exotic packaging to be
able to deliver it. Uh so people not uh
it, you know, forever it was a single
chip was the best way to package
everything fits on one chip and that's
what we're going to build. And now
there's these ideas of chiplets or
packaging multiple chips together. the
latest GPUs and I think the latest TPUs
has actually two what are called full
reticle design dyes package put into a
package and uh so a full reticle design
is uh the maximum you can build on a on
a semiconductor it they have a step and
repeat motor and there's you know in the
old days you'd have many chips inside
that now there's just one so two maximum
reticle designs form a node so they're
using packaging so if you from outside
you can say well there look there's look
how many transistors are it's quote
Moore's law is continuing but if you see
what's inside the chip you know that's
that has tapered off and I think part of
it is for a fair amount of the industry
if you were in a semiconductor
manufacturer and people ask you what you
do is I make Moors law I I make I
sustain Morris law what I do and if
you've been doing that for decades and
somebody says Morris law is over it's
like it my my career is
So I think there's an emotional side of
it but you know just look at the data
the data doesn't back up what Keller
says but I also didn't say that the
technology is not improving the
technology is continuing to improve and
specifically domain specific
architectures but if you look at the
general purpose architectures or even
other memory technologies you know it
used to be the DRAMs would improve by a
factor of four in density every 3 years
like clockwork and now it's maybe 10
years between factors for so you can see
plenty of evidence that Moore's law no
longer applies.
>> Is there um some new version or some
analog to Mo's law that is kind of
guiding uh you know microprocessor
design and architecture these days? I I
guess a question is uh both Nvidia and
Google are continuing to deliver much
faster processors for machine learning,
tremendously better. What are they
doing? Well, part of it is what I said
about uh packaging, you know, to getting
uh to to be able to get more transistors
and you keep them closer together
because distance matters. Uh part of it
is innovating on the floatingpoint
formats. So it you know unlike the
supercomputers of 64-bit
it's not even 64-bit not even 32-bit not
even 16 bit but 8bit and 4bit floating
point is as is going on so narrowing of
the data types um the uh you know having
kind of what's called the matrix
multiply instructions so these powerful
units that are put in there that can
that can uh do special purpose
applications that are very important get
making those bigger and faster. So those
are the things that are going on. But we
don't have this simplifying guideline
kind of underlying all this. You have to
be aware of each piece of the
technology, gauge how fast it's
improving, how whether it's they can
deliver on what's going on and then you
assemble that together and make your
bets. We're, you know, there's a paper
that we've just got approved that I
think we're going to put on archive
soon, which is, uh, talking about the
Google TPU line and pretty remarkably,
uh, the Google TPU line particularly for
training has stayed pretty constant in
the basic architecture design, uh,
things have gotten bigger and faster,
but the if you look at the the the
design of it, going back to the first
training TPU, it's that block diagram
still works.
uh all these you know a decade later. So
it you know the people who designed that
in whatever 2015 or two did a really
great job. Uh but the main components of
a a big matrix multiply unit the
so-called high bandwidth memory um uh a
vector unit to go with the matrix unit
and the basic building blocks are still
there. I think in your career with the
CPUs, benchmarks were a huge they played
a huge role in in measuring which
computer architectures were performant
and not in this this new space of uh
floatingoint operations for AI. Is there
a benchmark that people use for GPUs and
can you also apply it for TPUs?
>> I was you know I and some friends were
helped involved in called the ML Perf
effort. So it was inspired by the spec
CPU effort was the spec benchmarks that
there were these competing companies and
they'd all make claims about theirs was
better than the others and they realized
that wasn't good for the industry. So
they agreed on a set of benchmarks. So
the ML Perf effort is uh that's run now
but what's called ML comments is an
attempt to do that is if we're going to
do this comparisons
let's um let's let's not argue about
what the benchmarks are. So that's a
serious effort in that kind of
interestingly what's happened I'd say is
because
uh there's two pieces to u the design
there's the the machine learning
libraries that are uh to implement a lot
of features that you need for for these
applications and the libraries will even
be rewritten for specific applications
rather than just having general
libraries. This has turned out to be a
big advantage for Nvidia because they
have a large corporation with lots of
people that are available, lots of
engineers who could build these
libraries for them. So, it's turned out
um um not quite a it's not a it's not a
neutral evaluation, right? It's it's the
architecture plus the the libraries that
go with it and the compiler too, but
specifically the libraries that you
tailor each time. So Nvidia brings out
when they announce the new architecture
they create a new set of they modify the
libraries to run that really well or to
run applications really well. So that's
a powerful combination kind of in
business terms people referred to
Nvidia's having this CUDA moat but and
part of it is CUDA the programming
language but a big part of it is the
libraries that Nvidia Nvidia makes. So
this has made it difficult for for
startups to be able to compete with
Nvidia partly because
you know they didn't put enough emphasis
in the software and partly because you
know Nvidia just has many more engineers
than they do to be able to tailor the
libraries. So it's the libraries plus
the architecture that's this this
powerful advantage why most people do
things on GPUs. Now Google has been able
to develop their own libraries. Uh they
don't have as many engineers. They use
compilers more uh than I think Nvidia
does. So they they have a set of
libraries that they can do. But up until
recently, Google has
it's all been internal. It's just for
Google to use or you could use it via
the cloud. Um but uh you these startups
have u you know have to have a
difficulty as a result. That's why the
ML Perf hasn't been as popular. Not
everybody runs them because uh Nvidia
runs them really well, really better
than everybody else. And the startups
have a hard time showing off what they
can do uh given they don't have the the
engineering effort going into the
libraries that you need to do well in ML
Perf. you gave this popular talk about
how to have a bad career and it's kind
of uh the negation of advice to kind of
have a good career and I was just
wondering if you could kind of summarize
maybe the the top three things that you
kind of think people should take away.
>> Yeah. So, yeah. Well, there's been a few
things. So, the story is early in my
career my f a good friend and I said,
"How can we teach grad students how to
give a good talk?" And we thought it'd
be funny to explain how to give a bad
talk and then if you didn't want to give
a bad talk, this is so this is how to do
it badly and if you don't here's the
things to do not to do it badly. And so
then I later did a how to have a bad
career that's pretty much focused
towards uh academia you know so for
researchers to be able to do that. I
later did a how to have a bad uh
how to build a bad research center, how
to build a bad research lab. And then
recently I've been giving how to give AI
a bad carbon footprint. That's my latest
one. But I think the thing that might be
more relevant is uh at the end of my
talks I would I would kind of reflect on
my career and talk about lessons
learned. So I've written a paper called
uh lesson I think it's lessons life
lessons from the first half century of
my career. I wrote that recently. And so
those those are divided up into kind of
career advice and personal advice there.
On the the personal side, I'd say uh if
you have a family, you know, make sure
your families first, keep your family
first. Um the technology we've invented
makes it really easy for your, you know,
to take your work home with you and not
pay attention to your family. Uh, I had
a when I was first here at Berkeley, I
gave a senior faculty member a ride
home, dropped him off late at night
coming up from Silicon Valley and he
said, "Well, Dave, if I had to do it
over all over again, I wish I'd spent
more time with the family." And I never
wanted to say that. And nobody on their
deathbed says, you know, I wish I'd
spent more time in the office. So, so
you got to, you know, whenever it's easy
to kind of, you know, let the let your
career overcome the needs of your
family, but you just you got to just
remember that. Uh, I would say in my
life and kind of growing up in the 50s,
you know, the idea was to be happy, you
had to be wealthy. But those are
actually two different goals, wealthy
and happiness. So, I always made
decisions towards happiness versus
wealth. You come down with it. And I
felt very good about that. Uh I and even
now like why would I pick why would I
pick something that made me wealthy and
unhappy? Why would you do that? And so
uh and in the field that we're in it
turned out there was a lot of wealth to
go with it. So you know optimizing
happiness didn't mean you had to suffer
uh beyond that. Um I think it's
important to have fun. Personally, I
think when you're a kid, you don't have
to tell kids to play, but as an adult,
you get so busy. You you don't think you
have time to have fun. Uh, but you know,
you only get to do this once. So, uh, so
I right now I play soccer, I run my
bicycle to the interview, uh, I lift
weights, I body surf, I, you know, do
things with my wife and family and my
son. So, it it's important to have fun.
I think uh on the career side is one of
the uh pieces of advice is uh by a he
wrote this book the habits of very
effective people I think and he has a
little quadrant and he divides it of
urgent and not urgent and important and
unimportant and kind of there's so many
things in our technology like email and
texting to for you to focus on the
urgent things but you really shouldn't
shouldn't be spending a lot of time on
the unimportant urgent things. And it
takes self-discipline to set aside time
for the uh important non-urgent things.
But if you don't block that out, you can
just not have time to do anything. I get
to see other people's calendars at
Google and there's managers that every
half hour from 8 to 6, five days a week
are scheduled and I don't see how you
have time to think and reflect on things
like that.
Um, other career advice things is, uh, I
remember, uh, I kind of woke up one
morning and it was like God spoke to me.
I was like thunder struck. And it says
it's not how many things you start, it's
how many things you finish.
It seems relatively obvious, but you
know, I that's not the way I was acting.
I had they had many things going on. But
after that, it was like there's one main
thing I'm doing at time. So when
Hennessy and I wrote our textbook, that
was the main thing. when I was
department here, head here, that was the
main thing I did. Uh I would do some
other little things there. And John
Hennessy, he he wrote a book too, a kind
of a a career advice book based on his
presidency. And one of the things he
said in there, you know, you're only
going to be remembered for the five or
six things you've done in your life, not
for the hundreds of little things. So to
give yourself a chance to uh have some
things you're really proud of, it's
better to concentrate on a few of them
hoping that some of them will turn out
to be a big deal rather than scatter
yourself to to um many things. But if
you're interested, you can yeah, if you
look for life lessons, David Patterson
first half century, you can see the
whole list of I think there's 16 lessons
altogether.
you mentioned that uh you you didn't
want to reflect back on your life and
feel like you didn't have enough family
time and yeah, I've I don't think I've
ever heard anyone say the opposite. Why
do you think that is? Why is it that
everyone looks back on their life and
they never regret, you know, a lot of
family time? I I imagine there's got to
be at least one person that says, "I
spent too much time with my family.
[laughter]
>> My career suffered."
>> Yeah, my career suffered.
Well, you know what's you know what's
it's it's pretty philosophical. I mean
what's what's what's life all about?
What's success? Right? You have to you
have to figure out what that means for
you. I mean if if you have uh I don't
know if you have financial goals of
being a you know a millionaire or
billionaire or something like that and
that's how you judge your life.
Okay. Good luck. You know it's pretty
hard to make it. Uh it's pretty hard to
do. Um but I think it's the you know I
when I was finishing my PhD I read this
book by studs Turkl called working where
he interviewed all these people in his
careers and they look back and what they
liked and what they didn't like what
what they felt about their careers and
what I got out of it the people who
worked with people like ministers or
teachers or doctors uh felt really good
about what they did with their careers
and the people who did more ephemeral
stuff um you know like uh you know
technology things or airplanes or
something like that are long gone didn't
feel as good about it. It was the people
that they worked with that they really
cared about. And I went out with a
retired engineering dean here and he uh
into a meeting who I knew and he said,
you know, Dave, as I flinked my ear, it
was it wasn't the projects, it was the
people that I worked at the matter and I
thought I knew that from a long time
ago. So that's I mean this is kind of
senior persons offering advice. my I
think you're going to care more about
the people you've worked with uh and the
people you've helped will be a bigger
deal. That's part of and you know one of
the other things about personal
happiness is they studied happiness.
Psychologists used to just study crazy
people but they started like why are
people happy and they know what the
reasons are you know uh have a job that
you like you know have friends and
family helping other people helping
other people makes you happy that they
they know this having something kind of
either a religious side of it doesn't
have to be a formal religion but like
contact with nature the grandeur of
nature but the the kind of the list of
things you need to do to be happy is
well understood And uh and you know
there these h and there's our world is
filled with unhappy billionaires, right?
If money was the thing that made you
happy, why are these people very wealthy
people so mad about things. So yeah,
this is me passing on advice. In one of
your talks, you had uh it said what
worked well for me and it was kind of
some reflections and one of the things
in there I thought was unique and
interesting. You mentioned that courage
was a big part of your career and I I
don't hear that too often. I was curious
why you
>> uh say courage is so important in a
career. Yeah, I I I think that's I mean
that might be partially my personal
makeup, but you know I was uh I was I
was kind of the youngest kid in my class
and kind of small. It took me a while to
grow despite age. So I was always small
but I my parents encouraged me to go out
for wrestling and uh wrestling gives you
self-con physical self-confidence
because you you know spend years doing
that. that I did in high school and
college. And so I think uh partly you
know technically
uh you know having courage to do things
it kind of goes along with the advice is
fortune favors the bold. Uh that's this
that goes that's advice is 2,000 years
old. I mean it's hard to figure this
out. U Helen Keller wrote you know e
even even trying to play it safe you
still get caught. And so it turns out
you might as well you might fail no
matter what. And if you take a big
chance if that's you can succeed if you
don't take the chance you probably won't
succeed if you play it safe. So fortune
favors the gold. And I think it takes
courage to do that. I think also it just
for me intellectually I feel like if
there's something not right I need to
stand up and confront it. And I think
that kind of ironically comes from the
wrestling side of my personality where
if I see something somebody getting
picked on or something like that, I'm
I'm going to stand and try and stop it.
And I feel that that same responsibility
intellectually if people are making bad
arguments or doing doing something that
we need to stand up and do it. And I
feel good about that. The cautionary
part about that is uh as because I guess
one of my senior faculty members saw
this nature of me. He said one of the
sayings is friends come and go but
enemies accumulate. This is an old
saying. So if you think about it you
kind of people you went to high school
with a while friends you kind of forget
but somebody who you really does dislike
you never forget that you dislike that
person. So standing up when it's
important, but be careful when you make
enemies because you know they're going
to stick around for a long time.
>> When you say something's gone bad
technically, do you mean uh someone was
incorrect?
>> Yeah. When you know when they're weak,
you know, either politically or, you
know, or or technically when it's you
it's a weak argument, right? that that I
I think give us I think I really like
there to be a marketplace of ideas and
we hone the ideas by arguing them and so
if it's a if it's a specious argument
even if a person is you know a leader of
a company and it just doesn't make sense
I feel it's kind of the responsibil it's
better for the company if somebody
stands up and points that out than to
just let them get away with it and then
um and then and you know it's a little
bit confrontational
But, you know, as long as people all
agree that, you know, this is for the
greater good, we're going to we we need
to get the right ideas out there. And
so, let's argue about the ideas to to
see uh you know, polish them to make
them stronger. Uh I think that's
important in science, in engineering, um
and kind of uh in life too. There's a
lot of stuff going on right now in the
country that uh is worrisome and uh I've
certainly stood up and wrote opeds about
things that I think are wrong and need
to be corrected and uh you know if
people are afraid to do that
it's hard to be um optimistic about the
future if people are afraid to stand up
when when there's wrongs and uh try and
stop them. You also mentioned optimism
in the talk and you had this story I
wonder if you're willing to
>> sure. [laughter] So I would say in
engineering uh you know it's it's hard
to know right uh but I think you need to
be kind of optimistic or positive have a
positive outlook because so many things
could go wrong and then so my story
personal story that illustrates it's
going back to high school when I'm 16
I'm dating this very attractive girl and
I screw up my courage and ask her if we
would be exclusive at the time we the
phrase we used was going steady and she
looked at me and said And you know, she
was 16. She had dated other guys and
thought we were pretty young. And she
said, "Well, Dave, you're such a nice
guy. I don't know how to say no." For
me, as a logical person, I don't know.
Sounded like a yes. And so I hugged her
and said, "Great." And so she uh she in
her mind, she thought, "Well, I'll let
him down gently later." But we've been
married 59 years now, and she she hasn't
let me down yet. So that was a case
where optimism uh paid off.
>> I think everyone that hears a a healthy
relationship for that long, they might
wonder how you did it.
>> I used to tell people uh you know if you
go to if you go to weddings, the
marriage vows are really great, right?
But nobody can remember their wedding
vows. I used to say remember your
wedding vows, but nobody remembered
that. So we boiled it down to nine magic
words and it's just three sentences and
they start IU, I got to say all three
and it's I was wrong. you were right. I
love you. Okay, those are the those nine
words. And this applies to both both
partners in a relationship, not just one
partner. Uh but yeah, if you can say
them all and no substitutions, I was
wrong, you're right, you're a jerk. You
know, you can't do that. It's if you can
remember those nine words, that can help
you have a a long relationship like uh
my wife and I have. And then last
question for you, like knowing
everything you know now from your
career, if you could go back to yourself
when you had just entered the industry
and give yourself advice, what would you
say?
>> I mean, I think when I got here because
you know the imposttor syndrome, I was a
UCLA
graduate student and suddenly I'm a
Berkeley professor. So that just doesn't
seem like that was very intimidating.
But I after a while I just thought well
I'm probably not gonna get tenure so I
should just have a good time. So I think
I already I already had a right attitude
about it. I think that first year I
think it it was very stressful for my
while I was trying to handle the
imposttor syndrome and be a Berkeley
professor but I think after that I
handled it pretty well. I you know I I
did all the things with the kids and
stuff. So uh there's a version of that
question is like is there anything I
would do over again? There's one thing I
would have I was chair of the u of this
the architecture community the sig arch
as it's called and they have an annual
conference of the year and I was this
was in the 1990s I think I was the chair
and what I wasn't aware is at these
conferences there were men who were
harassing young women at this uh
conference I just didn't think you know
people like you know young people people
like me nobody would do that only an
idiot would do that can't possibly be
happening but it was happening and I
wish I somebody had said something to me
about it uh and because I would have I
would have straightened out any man
doing I would have threatened his life
if he were to do that today the only
comforting thing is Serita a who is a
famous computer architect uh she said
she also was not aware that that was
going on it became clear later you know
I mean uh uh five or 10 years later it
became more clear that this was going on
and there were mechanisms but that's the
one thing I wish you know if I could go
back in time I would have figured that
out and I would have straightened men
out who were doing that and they
wouldn't that would have stopped I
believe that would have stopped them
>> yeah [laughter]
thank you so much for your time today I
really appreciate it
>> all right and thanks for the interview
>> hey thank you for watching this podcast
if you liked it and you want to see the
show grow Please support with a comment
or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskoff, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. um this isn't the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within 8
hours of launching. I really appreciate
it if you were one of the people who
grabbed one of the early units. Um we're
now working on the long journey of
building the tooling now and so if you
still want to pick one up, I've left the
late pledges open on Kickstarter, so you
can grab one there. I'll put a link in
the description. Thank you again for
watching the podcast and I'll see you in
the next